foreign
[Music]
hey in this video we're going to have a
look at using a Sprite
a-s-e-p-r-i-t-e if you're not familiar
with this tool and we're going to use it
to create a nice space spriter 60 by 16
pixel
spaceship like we see here on the right
of the screen now this ship was created
with AI this comes from a tool called
leonardo.ai and I'll do a demo that
later on to show you can come up some
nice ideas for ship designs so a Sprite
is pretty cool it's a all in one Sprite
generating tool or a design tool I'm
going to go file new we've got new
Sprite
we want to say 16 by 16 pixels because I
make a little 16 by 16 pixel spaceship
if you want to make a set of spaceships
for instance maybe a bunch of little 16
by 16 Graphics we could make that wider
in fact I might do that I might make it
64 by 16.
okay we can say what color mode rgba is
the same as your standard Windows 16
million color rgba thing or if you have
an indexed pellet
um I'm going to be making this for the
ZX Spectrum next which has an indexed
uh palette I could leave it there
because I do have the palette stored
inside a Sprite but for now maybe we'll
do our GBA and then we'll use the
Spectrum uh color palette to bring it in
and convert it okay it's a transparent
background pretty good and then I'm
going to go okay
okay so I basically got four 16 by 16
squares here
okay we've got a bunch of tools here so
it's a full-on drawing tool give you
some mouse wheel to zoom in and out
and we can kind of draw pixels
everywhere now probably want to keep it
within that 16 by 16 block
cut undo
okay over here we have our palette
now up here we have a little load icon
you scroll down
we have a whole bunch of pellets from
different devices like M thread CPC
comic 64. pick 20 Game Boy
ms6 okay down the bottom I have ZX
Spectrum next
and I'm going to load
now you might be wondering how to get
the ZX Spectrum next um
basically ZX Spectrum next uh palette
and what I did was I used this tool here
this is Remy Sharps really awesome
graphic and audio and kind of everything
ZX Spectrum next development tool that
runs in the browser so up here under
Sprites
we go to the palette and this is the
general Spectrum default palette
okay and what we can do is we can go
download
and it saves us a DOT pal file so if I
saved as pal I can always come in here
and you can kind of just uh
options and you can get a load palette
and I'll actually take it from that.pel
file and
we'll put it into here so you can see
here it supports pal files act files
which are Adobe color
files if you have an adobe
palette
okay and all kinds of other things in
here too so I can extract it from
like for instance uh
that it'll extract the palette from a
Sprite that you load in Okay so
pretty easy to add that in I'm going to
go back to it
now I'm working in rgba so it's not
really using the fixed palette I can
select any color I like to draw in here
so I'm going to just clue let's clear
that first
edit and we should have a clear
option in here
okay delete there we go right okay so
back on to what we were supposed to be
doing and that's how we can use this uh
kind of like AI artwork or the an image
of a spaceship to create a nice simple
Sprite
the easiest way to kind of do that is
just to have a look at the shape I mean
this is the main thing this is too small
to do something that's detailed but this
is a good reference for form and color
and design that we can use as a basis
for drawing a Sprite because that's one
of the hard things when you're making
Sprites for a particular game is just
coming up with a cool looking shape so
having a little bit of inspiration or
reference to work from really useful and
it's probably recommended
like I said I'll show you how you can
use AI tools to generate a whole bunch
of inspiration so how do we get started
well we're going to just draw it you can
see there's some wings
looks like a kind of a bit of a cool jit
fighter if I ignore these lower wings
um so it's quite a cool shape little
spiky weapon thing there okay we have
lower Wings here with little looks like
engines on the back so this is a great
a great uh
kind of General reference for shape so
I'm going to go up here I could pick a
color from the palette
okay so maybe this color
which is very similar to this color
okay get to roughly the center okay it
does tell you down the bottom here in
the uh a Sprite will tell you where the
cursor is so
that's zero so that'll be seven
and eight will be our Center points
inside here so seven
let's just draw one that goes down
okay we'll just do it nice and centered
like that
okay
got like a little bit of wider here so
I'm going to just draw something I'm
using this kind of as a loose guide
just some kind of a cool shape
okay you know I just do one that goes
down a little bit sticky up there
okay it's not gonna be exact duplicate
little spiky things get on there
okay so I'm gonna also do these little
wings that kind of scoop in and come out
so
okay they're not going to be in 45
degree angle so I'm going to go up
down a little they look like they get a
bit wider down here
so this might be a 45 degree angle
sweet and I'm just gonna just paint in
these areas
okay so I'm going to change my blue
color okay I'll give a bit of shading on
here because it's quite good to have a
little bit of 3D kind of feel to it so
it's not just a flat color unless you
like a flat color Sprite like that
okay I might do there's a bit of a dark
laying down the center
so I'll pick a slightly darker Blue from
my palette here this one here
okay let's uh
do something like that I'm not going to
get too far in there
and I'm going to just uh
if we hook down the ALT key we can color
pick like in Photoshop let's get
this blue is slightly darker so which
side this is in Shadow so I'm going to
go down here
and do a slightly
darker blue and on the side
I'm gonna do a slightly lighter blue
which I think would be maybe this one
here it's a bit slightly lighter
okay I'm gonna put them here as well
just to give this color like a
shaded kind of look like that
now if you want to see what this looks
like normal size right at level 16
pixels down to the bottom here on a
Sprite you've got a little button that
says Show preview
okay and that's what it looks like there
we can zoom and zoom out on that if we
want to have a look
right so we've got that let's uh have a
look at we've got this kind of one game
down here okay now if you wanted to
color pick from here which isn't in the
palette you think well I'd kind of like
this blue if I could just get these
colors and use them in here and then
maybe
then we ask it to convert it to this
palette maybe that will be easy to draw
so what you do is go down here if you
want to pick from the screen put your
mouse over this color
Swatch left click
and then you move your mouse around by
holding down the left Mouse button and
you see is it Color Picker happens here
but you can also go off the application
and down here
and then pick a color
and let's just go
let's just do something else like that
I'm not doing an exact transition but
these are all the wings here now what I
might do
as I might also
put like a little bit of an engine in
there something maybe around here so I'm
going to hold down left Mouse button
drag it over here and kind of like this
yellowy orange color
good game
draw something like that
again I'm just using this as kind of a
shape guide my thing else okay so I'm
going to go in get back to my palette
here why not
there's some like little spiky bits
there like that okay it's not exactly
the same as that but let's uh put a dark
blue
canopy in there
maybe a really light
blue kind of like waitress bluish white
reflection
okay and then I might just add maybe it
like slightly lighter
highlight down the front there
okay I think on this side
well we might could do a little bit
darker maybe oh that's still light
okay that's the same color
and that's uh that's kind of the same
like that
okay and then we have like
basically a Sprite using this as a
reference to design an interesting
looking spaceship so nice way of getting
ships out really quick and you can kind
of see straight away that by having a
reference we can quickly bash out
something in almost no time because we
have a guide to the look we want now I'm
going to just fill in the background
with a bit of black
okay so I'm going to use the fill tool
in here which is I believe that
drop
there we go
there we go it looks kind of like that
it actually looks pretty cool once it's
on a black background
it's actually a pretty cool design okay
so that's one done
Let's uh undo the transparency we'll
bring it across and we'll just bring in
another design so what I'll do is rather
than bring in another design here I'll
go and show you how to use this AI tool
the AI tool I'm going to be using
is called Leonardo so Leonardo dot AI
you can go sign up there at the moment
I'm already signed up you can see I've
got uh
app.leonetto dot Ai and that's a kind of
a link to the thing we've got all kinds
of random weird rubbish gun on in here
because I've spent a little bit of time
yesterday just mucking around with kind
of ideas now if you haven't used a
there's some quite cool ones on the clo
collection
um anyway if you haven't used an AI tool
before one of these uh generative AI as
they're called
um they're pretty straightforward and
what you generally do is you just come
in and give it a text prompt so you just
put a descriptive text prompt and the AI
will try and interpret that and generate
the art or some kind of app for you so
you can think of this as a way of that
direction you're basically giving
direction to a virtual concept artist
and saying here's what I want come up
with some ideas for me so
not so much an artist but an art
director when using a tool like this
now it's a great tool for kind of ideas
and kind of like reference and things
like that you could go and Google but
normally I would just Google images and
find it collect inspiration and stuff
like that but this way it generates
something a bit more unique so it's not
just downloading someone's picture and
gluing it together it's actually
generating
some kind of more unique design from a
whole bunch of training that's had to
understand what certain kind of shapes
and forms are
so let's have a look let's go um what's
a good ship let's go a
sleek
jet aircraft
from the future
painted in a vibrant
red and gold
with a single
glowing
a single
powerful
jet engine okay now what I want it to do
is I want to do it as a what we call an
orthographic or a basically flat so it's
not like
and get rid of well attempt to say we
don't want anything that's too kind of
like perspectivey
um we want it to be a top down View
or I should say a top view
only
we want maybe a plan view so we put in
some descriptions in here we put in
maybe a few more
kind of phrases and terms and everything
else we'll go with that okay so we'll
start with this we'll see where we get a
model is just basically a training
system so basically it's a it's a big
chunk of data to generate different kind
of art Styles now like Leonardo
diffusion because that gives me this
really grungy realistic looking stuff
like that blue ship you saw before so
Leonardo diffusion that's sweet we've
got our General phrase here and we click
generate
okay it doesn't take too long
okay what I like about this Leonardo and
you've probably heard of some of these
other AI tools mid Journey stable
diffusion there's a whole range of these
things online Leonardo I like because it
gives you really oh look at that isn't
that nice okay some of these don't look
great because they're 3D they're on an
angle I really wanted a flat
orthographic top down view which is this
one here and that looks really sweet but
what I like about it is that it's got a
free and what I mean by free is well you
are limited per day you've got 150
tokens and basically tokens like a
credit and every image you generate
takes one token at the moment I have
four
if I look over here it actually tells me
this will use seven tokens and that's
probably just something to do with some
of these options in here I think it's to
do with the resolution
if I knock this down to 512 I get it
four tokens
as images get larger it uses a few more
and if you have some of these other
features on like prompt magic and it
takes 14 tokens now
I can also say Leonardo Styles or switch
these two options on so prompt magic
will try and interpret this slightly
differently and it might give us a
different result well it should give us
a different result so I'm going to click
generate
okay 9 10 11 12.
okay we'll see what it comes up with for
this one so I'm only going to do two
this is just to show you kind of a
how you can come up with some ideas some
inspiration to kind of Base Sprite
designs on
right
it's taking a little while
thinking this one's thinking because
usually when you put on prompt magic it
does a lot more kind of I guess thinking
behind and saying oh look at that okay
so this time it has picked up this a bit
more kind of like in context it's got
the top view
a plan view or top view it's got a
powerful jet engine
single one so it looks quite narrow so
it's got one engine in there it's a
vibrant red and gold
and it's a Sleek aircraft from the
future so it's got a very aircrafty look
to it okay so this has given us
a more accurate kind of interpretation
of that one so let's have a look at
these two I'm going to grab some of
these images and I'm going to just use
them to make a Sprite and this one here
is probably my favorite I like this I'm
going to click the download button which
will just open it and here so I'm going
to drag this off
okay now I'm using if you haven't seen
this before I'm using an image here here
that is actually really good if you've
got a Windows machine unfortunately it
is only Windows a Sprite in the other
hand Linux and Mac versions as well so
if you need this tool it's pretty cool
um
okay so here it is here so this is
called Earth and view Earth nv's been
around for decades I love this because
it's fast it's fast it opens a ton of
different image formats and you can also
save out in a bunch of different formats
as well what's also really cool is it
actually opens some retro file formats
like even Spectrum scr files I'm going
to spin this around because I want it
pointing up
so press the r key there we go
okay I'm just gonna shrink this a bit
make it a bit easier to see
let's Zoom that out a bit I'm not too
fast about looking super close at it
let's select that shape let's bring it
over the side here there we go okay so
on my second
area here I'm going to just draw this
kind of red and it's got this big
kind of like wide wing with spikes here
it's got some little Tails going down
there so let's see if we can kind of
come up with something like that
okay I'm gonna actually color pick from
this so
hold down the left Mouse button on this
color and let's pick
a red
and I'm going to just uh
oops I'm on the wrong tour I'm on the
fill tools though let's go brush
okay and bring it down
now I'm not going to worry about having
it a perfectly matched edge to edge I
want to have this nice nice skinny kind
of thing going on here
I might do it right to the top okay
I'm gonna go I'm gonna
bring it down like that and again I'm
just kind of using this more as a
reference guide for shade
because you know that's the
pretty
straight angular looking
something like that
that
sweet I've got a similar shape it's not
exactly the same but does mean I can
put these down here and have a little
tail out like that and that's a pretty
cool shape too very similar to the blue
one in terms of the just the form of the
shape
okay it's a little higher I might move
it down one pixel so there's a gap at
the top so I'm going to use the Marquee
tool inside uh a Sprite here
I'm gonna click it I'm going to move it
down look there you go
right okay so I've got a bit of black in
here looks like kind of a charcoal gray
um let's check if we can get something
off our palette here without color
picking
yeah it's pretty charcoal grayish oops
switch on the right tool might help
sweet okay let's go down
okay
and I'm Gonna Leave It kind of like that
that looks kind of
it's not exactly gray but hey
that's okay
okay I'm gonna get a black I'm gonna
draw some
canopy stuff in here
it's got like a double canopy which is
pretty cool
that
okay
got like a little looks like little
engine pods on here you're probably not
going to notice those
um but I'm gonna put something on there
anyway why not I'm gonna make them
purple
I'm getting kind of not being exact I'm
not exactly cloning that that's pretty
cool just add a bit of like interesting
detail to it splash of different color
Okay and like this one I could put some
a bit a bit of lighting though some a
bit of lighting uh
so maybe we'll just put like a little
bit of a
bright Edge on here so it gives that
kind of
um
idea of a little bit of highlight down
one side and let's put it down that one
too
on one side like that
just a little on there
and I might put on that side too
sweet okay so there's another ship
design
um
I'm gonna select the Marquee for this
one because I'm going to fill it in the
background with black now because I
hadn't got anything selected when I use
the fill tool it filled like the entire
junk but if I want to just fill in Arrow
a Sprite I just select the area using
this Marquee tool
use the fill tool Paint Bucket
and whoops wrong color let's pick black
done
okay and what I might do is pick a
really dark blue
because there's something loose this
gets the black background so oops
okay Ctrl D we'll just deselect that
okay so there's two ship designs right
there okay
so what we've looked at
what you've seen
is you've seen uh basically how to
quickly draw stuff how to use a Sprite
to get started you've seen uh how to
kind of like use the reference like that
to get some really
rough ideas or some inspiration for
drawing shapes and we've had a quick
look at Leonardo and generative AI tool
and how simple it is to just generate
like images or reference images
okay so I've got a few other ones in
here and I'll show you this in another
video that you can use to make like a
loading screens and things like that and
um
go ahead start making some spaceships